JUSTIN T. VAN DIJK

PROFILE

Human Geographer. Data scientist. Teacher. Interested in urban analytics, geo-demographics, urban transport, spatial inequalities, and big data applications in scarce data environments. Extensive experience in the domain of Geographic Information Systems, urban studies, and transport research. Possesses a wide skill set in the field of advanced spatial analysis, including experience with Python programming, R scripting, and PostgreSQL/PostGIS.

PRESENT APPOINTMENT

2018 - Present Postdoctoral research associate, University College London

Department of Geography. Geospatial Analytics and Computing Research Group. Working on the analysis and visualisation of big spatial population data sets; both historic and contemporary.

PREVIOUS APPOINTMENTS

2014 - 2017 **Junior lecturer** (part-time), Stellenbosch University

Department of Logistics. Tasks included thesis supervision of BSc (Honours) students and teaching the post-graduate course *Spatial Accessibility and Transport Network Analysis*.

2013 **Junior lecturer**, Utrecht University

Department of Human Geography and Planning. Tasks included thesis supervision of BSc students and teaching various undergraduate courses on Geographic Information Systems Human Geography and Planning.

2012 **Teaching assistant**, Stellenbosch University

Department of Logistics. Assistant in the course *Spatial Accessibility and Transport Network Analysis*.

2009 - 2012 **Teaching assistant**, Stellenbosch University

Department of Human Geography and Planning. Assistant in the courses Introduction to GIS, Transport Geography, and Advanced GIS.

EDUCATION

2014 - 2017 **Doctor of Philosophy**, Stellenbosch University

Transport Economics. Thesis: Designing Travel Behaviour Change interventions: A spatiotemporal perspective.

- 2011 2013 Master of Science, Utrecht University. GPA 4.0. Cum Laude.
 - Human Geography and Planning. Thesis: *Towards spatial justice: The spatial equity effects of a toll road in Cape Town, South Africa.*
- 2007 2011 Bachelor of Science, Utrecht University. GPA 4.0.

 Human Geography and Planning. Thesis: Contemporary Orientalism?

 Representations of Islam and Muslims in the Dutch Press: a content analysis of 'De Volkskrant' and 'De Telegraaf', 2001-2010.

REFEREED PUBLICATIONS: INTERNATIONAL JOURNALS

- 1. **Van Dijk**, **J. T.** and Longley, P. A., 2020, Interactive display of surname distributions in historic and contemporary Great Britain. *Journal of Maps*. Accepted for publication pending minor revisions.
- 2. Kandt, J., **Van Dijk, J. T.**, and Longley, P. A., 2020, Family name origins and inter-generational demographic change in Great Britain. *Annals of the American Association of Geographers*. In press. doi: 10.1080/24694452.2020.1717328
- 3. Engin, Z., **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, Lan, T., Longley, P. A., Treleaven, P., Batty, M., and Penn, A., 2019, Data-driven urban management: Mapping the landscape. *Journal of Urban Management*. Advance Online Publication. doi: 10.1016/j.jum.2019.12.001
- 4. **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, 2018, Identifying activity-travel points from GPS-data with multiple moving windows. *Computers, Environment and Urban System* 70: 84-101. doi: 10.1016/j.compenv urbsys.2018.02.004
- 5. **Van Dijk**, **J. T.** and Krygsman, S.C., 2017, Using GPS-based activity spaces and opportunity indicators for travel behaviour analysis. *Journal of Urban Technology* 25(2): 105-124. doi: 10.1080/19475683.2017.1340340
- 6. **Van Dijk**, **J. T.** and De Jong, T. 2017, Post-processing GPS tracks in reconstructing travelled routes in a GIS-environment: Network subset selection and attribute adjustment. *Annals of GIS* 23(3): 203-217. doi: 10.1080/10630732.2017.1400814
- 7. Idahosa, L. O. and **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, 2015, Freedom for whom in South Africa? Inequality, unemployment and the elderly. *Development* 58(1): 96-102. doi: 10.1057/dev.2015.18
- 8. **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, Krygsman, S. C., and De Jong, T., 2015, Towards spatial justice: The spatial equity effects of a toll road in Cape Town, South Africa. *Journal of Transport and Land use* 8(3): 95-114. doi: 10.5198/jtlu.2015.555

REFEREED PUBLICATIONS: INTERNATIONAL JOURNALS, UNDER CONSIDERATION

1. **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, Lansley, G., and Longley, P. A., 2020, Using linked consumer registers to estimate internal migration in the United Kingdom. *Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series A (Statistics in Society)*. Under review.

REFEREED PUBLICATIONS: IN PREPARATION

- 1. **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, Lansley, G., and Longley, P. A., 2020, Consumer data perspectives upon residential mobility in the UK housing market.
- 2. **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, Lansley, G., and Longley, P. A., 2020, Using linked consumer and administrative data to model demographic changes. In: Clarke, G., Birkin, M., and Stimson, B. (Eds.), Applications of Big Data in geography and planning.

REFEREED PUBLICATIONS: BOOK CHAPTERS

1. Wolfensberger M., Dekker, M., **Van Dijk, J. T.**, Zubizarreta, J., Hait, C., Mann, C., and Lucas, C., 2013, Learning as salon: Honors International Collaboration. In: Mulvaney, M. K. and Klein, K. (Eds.), Preparing Tomorrow's Global Leaders: Honors International Education (pp. 75-84). Lincoln: National Collegiate Honors Council. NCHC Monograph Series.

REFEREED PUBLICATIONS: CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS

- 1. **Van Dijk**, **J. T.** and Longley, P. A., 2019, Platial geo-temporal demographics using family names. In: Westerholt, R. and Mocnick, F.-B. (Eds.), *Proceedings of the 2nd International Symposium on Platial Information science (PLATIAL'19)*. Warwick: Warwick University.
- 2. **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, Lansley, G., Lan, T., and Longley, P. A., 2019, Using the spatial analysis of family names to gain insight into demographic change. *Proceedings of the 27th Conference of GIS Research UK (GISRUK)*. Newcastle: Newcastle University.
- 3. Lan, T., Lansley, G., **Van Dijk**, **J. T.**, and Longley, P. A., 2019, Geocoding historical census records in England and Wales. *Proceedings of the 27th Conference of GIS Research UK (GISRUK)*. Newcastle: Newcastle University.
- 4. **Van Dijk**, **J. T.** and Krygsman, S. C., 2016, Mobile technologies for data collection in sub-Saharan Africa: An outlook to the future of mobility research. #CelebrateGeography: Proceedings of the 11th Biennial Conference of the Society of South African Geographers (SSAG 2016). Stellenbosch: SunMedia. 180-189.
- 5. **Van Dijk, J. T.** and Krygsman, S. C., 2015, Gathering individual travel data with GPS-enabled smartphones: A proof of concept study. *Proceedings of the 34th Southern African Transport Conference (SATC 2015). Pretoria: Southern Africa Transport Conference*. 448-460.

PROFESSIONAL PUBLICATIONS

1. **Van Dijk**, **J. T.** and De Jong, T., 2010, Medische voorzieningen in kaart. Bereikbaarheid medische voorzieningen in Bushbuckridge, Maruleng en Sekhukhune [Accessibility of Medical services in Bushbuckridge, Maruleng and Sekhukhune]. *Geografie* 19 (5): 18-20.

GRANTS

2015 - 2017	NRF-DST innovation scholarship, National Research Foundation and Department of Science and Technology ZAR 330,000
2016	Postgraduate travel grant, National Research Foundation ZAR 24,222
2015 - 2016	Stellenbosch merit bursary, Stellenbosch University ZAR 50,000
2014 - 2016	Scholarship award for full-time doctoral studies, Stellenbosch University

PAPERS PRESENTED AT INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCES

ZAR 390,000

- 1. "Platial geo-temporal demographics using family names". 2nd International Symposium on Platial Information science. *Warwick, United Kingdom, September 5 September 6, 2019.*
- 2. "Using the spatial analysis of family names to gain insight into demographic change". 27th Conference of GIS Research UK. *Newcastle, United Kingdom, April 23 April 26, 2019.*
- 3. "Mobile data collection techniques in sub-Saharan Africa: An outlook to the future of transport research". 11th Biennial Conference of the Society of South African Geographers. *Stellenbosch, South Africa, September 25 September 25, 2016.*
- 4. "Designing a Voluntary Travel Behaviour Change Intervention: Smartphones and Space-Time Accessibility Analysis". Mobile Tartu 2016. *Tartu, Estonia, June 29 – July 1, 2016*.
- 5. "Gathering individual travel data with GPS-enabled smartphones: A proof of concept study". 34th Southern African Transport Conference. *Pretoria, South Africa, 6 July July 9, 2015.*
- 6. "Twenty years of Freedom: The role of the Old Persons Grant in addressing unemployment and inequality in a young democracy". 12th Development Dialogue "Rethinking Democracy". *The Hague, the Netherlands, October 16 October 17, 2014.*
- 7. "Towards spatial justice: The spatial Equity Effects of a Toll Road in Cape Town, South Africa". World Symposium on Transport and Land Use. *Delft, the Netherlands, June 24 June 27, 2014.*

GUEST LECTURES AND INVITED RESEARCH SEMINARS

- "What's in a name? Storing surname geographies for both visualisation and analysis". Guest lecture Graduate School Economic and Management Sciences. Stellenbosch University, South Africa, March 8, 2019.
- 2. "What's in a name? Storing surname geographies for both visualisation and analysis". Geo+Data London (AGI/CDRC event). University College London, United Kingdom, December 4, 2018.
- 3. "Using GPS-enabled smartphones for Voluntary Travel Behaviour Change interventions". Guest lecture Utrecht University Summer School on "GPS data analysis". Utrecht University, the Netherlands, July 12, 2017.
- 4. "GPS data analysis". Guest lecture Utrecht University in the course "Introduction to GIS". Utrecht University, the Netherlands, February 18, 2016.
- 5. "GPS data analysis". Guest lecture Utrecht University in the course "Introduction to GIS". Utrecht University, the Netherlands, November 25, 2015.

ENABLING ROLES	
2019 - Present	Undergraduate dissertation supervision
	Co-supervisor undergraduate dissertation. Institute of Education, University
	College London.
2019	"Technical Tuesdays" seminar series
	Co-organiser and speaker in this weekly Seminar Series on methods and
	techniques for quantitative researchers.
2019	Nuffield Research Placement supervision
	Supervision of first-generation prospective university student.
2014 - 2015	Social Sciences for Development conference

2016 - 2017 Harambee Youth Employment Accelerator

2015 conference.

Data analysis using well-known statistical techniques as well as more advanced machine learning classifiers for Harambee Youth Employment Accelerator to better understand, and possibly predict, successful job placements.

Member of the local organising committee at Stellenbosch University for the

PROJECTS

2019 - Present Gamble Aware

Data analysis and visualisations on the geographical distribution of supply

and demand for treatment and support for problematic gamblers.

2019 Greater London Authority

Preparation of selected data products on ethnicity, population churn,

migration, and social mobility for the Greater London Authority.

2018 - Present GBNames website

Website development. GBNames explores the spread of family names across Great Britain, using historic censuses and recent consumer registers, and links surnames to consumer data statistics. The alpha version of the

website is accessible through: https://data.cdrc.ac.uk/gbnames/.

2016 - 2017 Human Sciences Research Council

Contributions project proposal for funding the establishment of a nationally

representative cell phone panel of South Africans.

2009 AfriScope

Contributions to a study on the accessibility of government services in the

Integrated Sustainable Rural Development (ISRD) Nodes in South Africa.

REVIEW

2020 Journal of Transport Geography

Transactions in GIS

2019 Transactions in GIS

Journal of Transport Geography

The Israel Science Foundation (Grant review)

Journal of Traffic and Transportation Engineering

2018 Journal of Transport Geography

Computers, Environment, and Urban Systems

2016 Area Development and Policy

2015 Journal of Transport and Land Use

CORE TECHNICAL SKILLS

Geographic Information Systems R, Python, Q-GIS, ArcGIS

Data processing R, Python, Bash, GNU Parallel

Data analysisR, PythonData visualisationggplotProject managementGit, GitHubWeb mappingLeaflet.js

Web development HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Django

Database management PostgreSQL Typesetting LaTeX

LANGUAGE PROFICIENCY

Dutch Native proficiency

English Full professional proficiency isiXhosa Basic conversational proficiency

REFERENCES

Professor Paul Longley

Professor of Geographic Information Science, University College London **E** p.longley@ucl.ac.uk **T** +44 (0) 20 7679 0500

Professor James Cheshire

Professor of Geographic Information and Cartography, University College London

E james.cheshire@ucl.ac.uk **T** +44 (0) 20 7679 0513

Dr Jens Kandt

Lecturer in Urban Geography and Data Science, University College London

E j.kandt@ucl.ac.uk **T** +44 (0) 20 3108 3880

Dr Neil Rankin

Extraordinary Associate Professor Economics, Stellenbosch University

Data scientist, Predictive Insights

E neil@predictiveinsights.net **T** +27 (0) 21 808 2678